# Kimberly A. Dill-McFarland, PhD

Bioinformatician

Division of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, University of Washington 1-206-595-1828; kdillmcfarland@gmail.com

in 💟 💆 kdillmcfarland; https://kdillmcfarland.github.io/

Microbiology PhD with 9+ years experience in applying data science and statistics to biological problems. Skilled leader of teams with diverse backgrounds and varied training. Expertise in next-generation sequencing from experimental design to publication. Effective communicator with formal teaching experience. Specific skills include:

Data	Software	Statistics
Transcriptomics: RNA-seq Genetics: MegaEX, Omni, whole exome Epigenetics: ATAC-seq, bisulfite seq Proteomics: MS/MS Microbiome: 16S, 18S, ITS, meta- transcriptomics	AWS Git, GitHub R, Rmd, Shiny samtools, bedtools STAR, BWA, bowtie PLINK, vcftools mothur, QIIME	Linear, PLS, LASSO, latent regression Un/supervised machine learning PCA, NMDS, tSNE Sparse data imputation Data visualization
	monui, willyic	

### **EXPERIENCE**

07/2019 - present Bioinformatician, Allergy and Infectious Diseases, U. of Washington

- Analyze human transcriptomic, epigenetic, and genetic datasets including quality assessment, and statistical tests
- Develop novel pipelines for integrated 'omics analysis
- Lead a team of 3 core bioinformaticians as well as mentor post-docs and students in related groups
- Administrator AWS Organization (6 users)

04/2021 - present **Genomic data specialist.** San Mateo County Public Health Lab (part-time)

> Genome assembly, variant tracking, and outbreak assessment of COVID-19 clinical samples

08/2017 - 06/2019 Post-doctoral research fellow, Microbiology & Immunology, U. of British Columbia

- Directed Experiential Data Science for Undergraduate Cross-disciplinary Education (EDUCE) including a team of 3 teaching assistants
- Designed and implemented data science curriculum in 7 courses
- **ECOSCOPE** fellow coordinating and teaching data science workshops for industry and academic partners

07/2016 - 06/2017 Post-doctoral research associate, Bacteriology/Sociology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Investigated relationships between the human gut microbiome and longterm behaviors in the Wisconsin Longitudinal Study (WLS)
- Navigated large, longitudinal survey databases

08/2011 - 06/2016 Graduate research assistant, Bacteriology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Designed and implemented amplicon sequence analysis pipelines
- Collaborated effectively with diverse international researchers resulting in first and corresponding author publications
- Mentored high school, undergraduate, and graduate students

## **EDUCATION**

2011-2016	Ph.D. Microbiology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI. GPA: 4.00
2007-2011	<b>B.S. Molecular and cellular biology</b> , Minor mathematics, U. of Puget Sound, Tacoma, WA. GPA: 3.84

### **SELECT PUBLICATIONS**

Full publication list

**Dill-McFarland KA**, König SG, Mazel F, Oliver DC, McEwen LM, Hong KY, Hallam SJ. 2021. An integrated, modular approach to data science education in microbiology. <u>PLoS Comput Biol</u> In press. doi: <u>10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008661</u>

**Dill-McFarland KA**, Tang Z, Kemis JH, Kerby RL, Chen G, Palloni A, Sorenson T, Rey FE<sup>†</sup>, Herd P<sup>†</sup>. 2019. Close social relationships correlate with human gut microbiota composition. <u>Sci</u> Rep 9: 703. doi: 10.1038/s41598-018-37298-9

**Dill-McFarland KA**, Weimer PJ, Breaker JD, Suen G. 2018. Diet influences early microbiota development in dairy calves without long-term impacts on milk production. <u>Appl Environ Microbiol</u> 85(2): e02141-18. doi: 10.1128/AEM.02141-18

## **CURRENT PROJECTS**

**Dill-McFarland KA**, Schwartz JT, Fulkerson PC, Zhao H, Shao B, Altman MC, Gill MA. Eosinophil-mediated suppression and Anti-IL-5 enhancement of plasmacytoid dendritic cell interferon responses in asthma. <u>J Allergy Clin Immunol</u>. In revision

**Dill-McFarland KA**, Peterson G, Nguyen F, Penchek P, Stein CM, Mayanja-Kizza H, Boom WH, Hawn TR. Epigenetic programming of lipoprotein pathways associated with resistance to tuberculosis. In prep

**Dill-McFarland KA**, Busse W, Altman MC, Rosenkranz M. Links between allergen-induced gene expression in the lung and neurological responses in asthma. In prep

#### NOTABLE ACCOMPLISHMENTS

2017, 2018, 2019	Session convener American Society for Microbiology (ASM) Microbe meeting
2016	Microbiome Digest's Best Microbiome Paper
2016	Sigrid Leirmo Memorial Award for peer mentorship and support
2009, 2010	American Society for Microbiology Undergraduate Research Fellow

References available upon request